<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE xliff PUBLIC "-//XLIFF//DTD XLIFF//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/xliff/documents/xliff.dtd">
<xliff version="1.0">
  <file source-language="EN" target-language="en" datatype="plaintext" original="messages" date="2012-04-22T18:51:56Z" product-name="messages">
    <header/>
    <body>
      <trans-unit id="1">
        <source>Listagem de eventos</source>
        <target>List of Events</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="2">
        <source>Português</source>
        <target>Portuguese</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="3">
        <source>Inglês</source>
        <target>English</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="4">
        <source>Bem vindo</source>
        <target>Welcome</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="5">
        <source>Home</source>
        <target>Home</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="6">
        <source>Catálogo</source>
        <target>Catalog</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="7">
        <source>Visita Guiada</source>
        <target>Guided Tour</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="8">
        <source>Contactos</source>
        <target>Contacts</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="9">
        <source>Sair</source>
        <target>Logout</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="10">
        <source>Entrar/Registar</source>
        <target>Login/Create Account</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="11">
        <source>Telefone</source>
        <target>Phone Number</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="12">
        <source>FAX</source>
        <target>FAX</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="13">
        <source>E-Mail</source>
        <target>E-Mail</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="14">
        <source>Utilizador criado.</source>
        <target>User created.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="15">
        <source>Registo</source>
        <target>Create Account</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="16">
        <source>Voltar</source>
        <target>Back</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="17">
        <source>Registar</source>
        <target>Create Account</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="18">
        <source>Login</source>
        <target>Login</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="19">
        <source>Se ainda não tem conta, registe-se aqui</source>
        <target>If you don't have an account, click here</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="20">
        <source>Entrar</source>
        <target>Login</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="21">
        <source>Oops! The page you have asked for is restricted and you cannot gain access without authorisation.</source>
        <target/>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="22">
        <source>Login below</source>
        <target/>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="23">
        <source>Museu do ISEP</source>
        <target>The ISEP Museum</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="24">
        <source>Instalado no ISEP, o Museu foi criado em 1998 e possui um numeroso espólio de instrumentos científicos datados, na sua grande maioria do séc. XIX.</source>
        <target>Located at ISEP, the Museum was established in 1998 and has a large collection of scientific instruments dated in is vast majority of the 20th century.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="25">
        <source>Sendo o ISEP uma escola de carácter tecnológico, desde cedo teve necessidade de adquirir objetos que demonstrassem de forma clara a evolução científica e técnica, muito importante no ensino experimental de então.</source>
        <target>Being ISEP a school of technological nature, since the beginning there was the need to acquire objects that clearly demonstrate the scientific and technical developments, very important resources in experimental teaching those days. </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="26">
        <source>A sua coleção, que documenta a história das engenharias dos últimos 155 anos, estende-se a quase todas as áreas lecionadas neste estabelecimento, da física à eletrotécnica, da matemática à mecânica, da engenharia química à civil sem esquecer a copiosa coleção de mineralogia.</source>
        <target>The collection, which documents the history of engineering of the past 155 years, extends to almost all areas taught by this institution, from physics to electrotechnics, from mathematics to mechanics, from chemical engineering to civil engineering not forgetting the copious collection of mineralogy.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="27">
        <source>Para além dos objetos, o museu do ISEP, possui ainda um considerável espólio bibliográﬁco onde podemos encontrar grandes obras de referência como a enciclopédia de Diderot e Alembert, um precioso livro de física de Musschenbroeck ou um livro de arquitetura de Leon Battista Alberti.</source>
        <target>In addition to the objects, the Museum of the ISEP has a noteworthy bibliographical collection where we can find major reference works such as the encyclopedia of Diderot and Alembert, a precious physics book of Musschenbroeck or an architecture book of Leon Battista Alberti. </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="28">
        <source>Últimas Notícias</source>
        <target>Lastest News</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="29">
        <source>Últimas Peças</source>
        <target>Highlights</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="30">
        <source>Informações Úteis</source>
        <target>Useful Information</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="31">
        <source>Morada</source>
        <target>Address</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="32">
        <source>Sala de Desenho</source>
        <target>Drawing Room</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="33">
        <source>Sala de Civil, Metalúrgica e Hidráulica</source>
        <target>Civil, Metallurgic, Hydraulic Room </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="34">
        <source>Sala de Química</source>
        <target>Chemistry Room</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="35">
        <source>Sala de Mecânica</source>
        <target>Mechanics Room</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="36">
        <source>Sala de Física, Eletrotécnia e Geometria Descritiva</source>
        <target>Physics, Electrotechnology, Descriptive Geometry Room</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="37">
        <source>Descarregar video</source>
        <target>Download video</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="38">
        <source>Formato MP4</source>
        <target>MP4 format</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="39">
        <source>Formato Ogg</source>
        <target>Ogg format</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="40">
        <source>O estudo da física esteve presente na escola desde a sua criação. Na década de 70 do séc. XIX o gabinete de física continha uma numerosa e muito escolhida coleção de máquinas e aparelhos, em todos os ramos ou sessões da física experimental, que satisfazia as necessidades do ensino da época e estava preparado para acolher os novos inventos que entretanto surgiam.</source>
        <target>The study of physics was present at the school since its foundation. In the 70’s of the XIX century the physics office contained a numerous and chosen collection of machines and equipment, in all fields or sessions of experimental physics, which fulfilled the needs of the teaching at the time and was prepared to receive the new inventions that meanwhile emerged.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="41">
        <source>Na reforma do ensino industrial, foi criado o Gabinete Eletrotécnico que era destinado às experiências necessárias para as lições e para exempliﬁcação e ensino das diversas aplicações da eletricidade. Atualmente esta coleção também possui alguns objetos pertencentes à antiga Escola Prática de telegraﬁa que era destinada ao ensino do uso e manipulação dos aparelhos telegráﬁcos e telefónicos dos diversos sistemas que ﬁcariam instalados, após algumas obras no edifico, no extinto convento das Carmelitas, onde já tinha funcionado a Repartição Central dos Telégrafos da cidade do Porto.</source>
        <target>The reform of industrial education, created the Electrotechnical Office that was designed to the necessary experiences for the lessons and for exemplification and teaching of the various applications of electricity. Nowadays this collection has also some objects belonging to the former Practical School of Telegraphy witch taught the use and handling of telegraph and telephone apparatus witch would be installed, after a few works in the building, in the former convent of the Carmelitas, where the Central Office of the Telegraphs of the city of Oporto has already functioned.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="42">
        <source>A geometria descritiva foi desde o início uma importante disciplina na formação dos alunos da escola. Foi comprado diverso material para o ensino prático, entre eles, em 1868 um conjunto de trinta modelos de ﬁguras de geometria descritiva, desde a projeção das linhas até à penetração dos sólidos, todos iguais aos que havia no Conservatório de Artes e Ofícios de Paris, que podem ser hoje contemplados no nosso museu.</source>
        <target>The descriptive geometry was from the beginning an important subject in the school  students training. In 1868 different materials were bought for practical teaching: thirty models of figures of descriptive geometry, from projection of the lines to the penetration of solids, all equal to those at the Conservatory of Arts and Crafts of Paris, which can be seen today in our museum.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="43">
        <source>História</source>
        <target>History</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="44">
        <source>O estudo da Física esteve sempre presente na Escola. Em 1855 e após a instalação definitiva da escola no Edifício da Graça o Gabinete de Física é partilhado pela Escola e pela Academia Politécnica durante vários anos.</source>
        <target>The study of physics has always been present at school. In 1855 and after the final accommodation of the school in the Building  of  Grace,  the Physics  Office  was shared with the Polytechnic School and Academy for several years.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="45">
        <source>No registo oficial, o Gabinete de Física apenas passa a existir oficialmente em 1864, após a reforma do ensino industrial.</source>
        <target>In the official record, the Physical Office only becomes official in 1864, after the reform of industrial education. </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="46">
        <source>Entre 1891 e 1911 o Gabinete possuiu outro nome, denominado de Gabinete e Laboratório de Física, voltando após este intervalo ao nome anterior</source>
        <target>Between 1891 and 1911 the Office had another name,  Office and  Laboratory of Physics, returning after the interval to the previous name.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="47">
        <source>Na década de 50, devido ao facto de o número de alunos ter aumentado bastante, foi elaborado um estudo para a criação de um novo laboratório de Física. Nos anos mais recentes e devido às necessidades do próprio ensino, o Departamento de Física reestruturou os seus laboratórios, passando a existir atualmente por exemplo, o Laboratório da Câmara Escura.</source>
        <target>In the '50s, due to the increased  number of students, a study was undertaken to create a new physics lab. In recent years and due to the needs of teaching itself, the Physics Department has restructured its laboratories, creating for example, Darkroom Laboratory.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="48">
        <source>A Geometria Descritiva e Estereotomia</source>
        <target>Descriptive geometry and Stereotomy</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="49">
        <source>O estudo da Geometria Descritiva foi desde início de estrema importância para a formação dos alunos na escola.</source>
        <target>The study of descriptive Geometry was from the beginning of extreme importance to the training of students at school.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="50">
        <source>Em 1864, após mais uma reforma, as cadeiras foram alteradas e foi introduzido o estudo da Estereotomia.</source>
        <target>In 1864, after another reform, the subject changed and the study of Stereotomy was introduced.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="51">
        <source>O ensino da Geometria e da Estereotomia esteve sempre presente ao longo dos anos no estabelecimento de ensino, embora os nomes das disciplinas tenham variado com as contínuas reformas que foram ocorrendo ao longo dos anos.</source>
        <target>The teaching of Geometry and Stereotomy was always present over the years in the school, although the names of subjects have changed due to the reforms that have occurred over the years.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="52">
        <source>Hoje em dia existem ainda disciplinas referentes a Geometria e Estereotomia nos cursos de Engenharia Civil e Geotécnica.</source>
        <target>Today there are still subjects related to this two subjects in the Civil Engineering and  Geotechnics degrees.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="53">
        <source>Gabinete Eletrotécnico</source>
        <target>Electrotechnical Office</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="54">
        <source>O Gabinete Eletrónico foi criado em 1886 aquando da reforma do ensino industrial. Este gabinete, por falta de espaço no Edifício da Graça, foi instalado no Convento das Carmelitas.</source>
        <target>The Electrotechnical Office was created in 1886 when the reform of industrial teaching. This office, due to lack of space in the building of Grace, was installed at the Convento das Carmelitas.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="55">
        <source>Em 1981, após mais uma reforma dos Institutos Industriais e Comerciais, tanto o Gabinete Eletrotécnico como a disciplina foram descontinuadas, voltando ao ativo apenas em 1911. Contudo, ressalva-se que em 1905 foi introduzido o curso de Eletrotecnia.</source>
        <target>In 1981, after another reform of the Industrial and Commercial Institutes, both the Electrotechnical Office and the respective subject ended, and returned to activity only in 1911. However, it is important to refer that in 1905 the Electrotechnology degree was introduced.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="56">
        <source>Como referido anteriormente, em 1911 dá-se o regresso do Gabinete e Laboratório de Eletrotecnia e a partir de 1931 este passou a denominar-se de Laboratório de Eletricidade.</source>
        <target>As mentioned before, in 1911 the Office and Laboratory of Electrotechnology reappeared and it was renamed Electricity Laboratory in 1931.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="57">
        <source>Hoje em dia, existem no departamento de Eletrotecnia diversos laboratórios que dão suporte às aulas práticas dos diversos ramos do curso.</source>
        <target>Nowadays, in Electrotechnology Department  there are several laboratories that support the teaching practices of the numerous branches of the degree.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="58">
        <source>Escola prática de Telegrafia</source>
        <target>Practical School of Telegraphy</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="59">
        <source>Por intermédio do desenvolvimento dos meios de comunicação, a Telegrafia foi introduzida no Ensino Industrial em 1864, com a criação do curso de Telegrafistas.</source>
        <target>Through the development of means of communication, Telegraphy was introduced in Industrial Education in 1864 with the creation of the degree of Telegraphers.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="60">
        <source>Após a reforma de 1886, este curso passou a denominar-se de Curso de Correios e Telégrafos. Foi criada também uma Escola Prática de Telegrafia.</source>
        <target>After the reform of 1886, this degree was renamed to Degree of Mail and Telegraphs. It was also created the Practical School of Telegraphy.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="61">
        <source>Na restruturação do ensino em 1891 o Curso de Telegrafista é suprimido, deixando também de ser referenciada a Escola Prática de Telegrafia.</source>
        <target>By the time of the restructure of education in 1891, the Telegraph Degree is suppressed, and the Practical School of Telegraphy were extinguished.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="62">
        <source>Em 1905 reaparece o curso de Telégrafos, com a duração de 3 anos.</source>
        <target>In 1905 the Telegraph  degree reappears, with the duration of three years.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="63">
        <source>No ano de 1911, foi criado o Gabinete e Laboratório de Eletrotecnia onde estariam os aparelhos telegráficos.</source>
        <target>In 1911, the Office and Laboratory of Electrotechnology was created and all the telegraph instruments were placed there.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="64">
        <source>Em 1919, após mais uma reforma do Ensino Industrial e Comercial, passa a existir o Curso Especializado de Eletrotecnia, tendo terminado o ensino de Telegrafia.</source>
        <target>In 1919, after an Industry and Commerce Education reform, the specialized degree of Electrotechnology was created, and ended the teaching of Telegraphy.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="65">
        <source>Com a criação da Escola Industrial em 1852, a instalação do laboratório químico foi sempre uma preocupação e desde logo foi adquirido diverso material para o ensino prático da química. O Conselho Escolar do Instituto considerava que este estabelecimento era uma das repartições de ensino prático mais importantes.</source>
        <target>With the creation of the Industrial School in 1852, the installation of the chemical laboratory was always a concern and since then a variety of materials for the practical teaching of chemistry has been acquired. The School Board of the Institute considered that this institution was one of the most important practical training divisions. </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="66">
        <source>O laboratório químico era destinado não só a preparar as experiências necessárias às lições orais da cadeira de química e às manipulações dos alunos para complemento do ensino teórico mas, também para fazer análises, experiências e ensaios, que lhes eram incumbidos pelo governo ou solicitados pelos particulares. Era também destinado à realização de investigações científicas ou tecnológicas ordenadas pelo respetivo diretor, ministrar o ensino da química prática aos indivíduos estranhos ao Instituto, que se dedicavam à indústria e facilitar aos particulares a execução de quaisquer análises ou trabalhos compatíveis com o ensino.</source>
        <target>The chemical laboratory was designed not only to prepare the necessary experiments to the oral lessons and chemical manipulations of the students as a complement to the theoretical, but also to do analysis, experiments and tests, asked by the government or requested by private individuals. It were also made scientific and technologic researches order by the director, teaching of practical chemistry to persons not belonging to the Institute but engaged to the industry, and facilitate the implementation of analysis or works related to the teaching.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="67">
        <source>A coleção existente no museu é composta por inúmeros utensílios vulgarmente utilizados nos laboratórios químicos, como pipetas, buretas, areómetros, balões, retortas, e instrumentos, como polarímetro, vino-colorímetro, microscópios, balanças, entre outros.</source>
        <target>It has also a collection of different tools commonly used in chemical laboratories, such as pipettes, burettes, hydrometers, flasks, retorts, and instruments like polarimeter, vino-colorimeter, microscopes, scales, among others. </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="68">
        <source>Uma das prioridades após a criação da escola industrial em 1852 foi a criação do Laboratório Químico, fundamental para o funcionamento da 7ª cadeira – Química Aplicada às Artes.</source>
        <target>One of the priorities after the creation of the industrial school in 1852 was the establishment of the Chemical Laboratory, essential to the functioning of the 7th discipline – Chemistry Applied to Arts.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="69">
        <source>A escassez de espaço para instalar o Laboratório obrigou o órgão dirigente da escola a considerar várias alternativas para ver finalmente a cadeira a ser lecionada.</source>
        <target>The lack of space to install the laboratory forced the school board to consider various alternatives in order to see the teaching of this subject.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="70">
        <source>O Conselho Escolar da Escola considerava que este estabelecimento era uma das repartições de ensino prático mais importantes, ao qual o referido conselho pretendia dar maior desenvolvimento, pelas vantagens que poderia trazer para o ensino da Química aplicada às Artes e para a Indústria em geral.</source>
        <target/>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="71">
        <source>Após a reforma de 1886, o Laboratório Químico ganhou uma maior importância, agregando à sua componente meramente teórica uma maior capacidade a nível da experiência e da investigação. Muitas das experiências eram incumbidas por intermédio do Governo ou solicitadas por parte das organizações particulares.</source>
        <target>After the 1886 reform, the Chemical Laboratory has gained greater importance, adding to its theoretical  component an higher level of experience and research. Many of the experiments were tasked through the Government or requested by the private organizations.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="72">
        <source>Ao longo das várias reformas foram surgindo inúmeros laboratórios, atualmente ligados ao ensino da Química: o Laboratório de Eletroquímica e Corrosão, o Laboratório de Química Analítica, o Laboratório de Química Orgânica e Bioquímica Microbiana, o Laboratório de Química Analítica Qualitativa, o Laboratório de Tecnologia Química, entre outros.</source>
        <target>Throughout the various reforms many laboratories were established, and cue today linked to the teaching of chemistry: the Laboratory of Electrochemistry and Corrosion, Laboratory of Analytical Chemistry, the Laboratory of Microbial Organic Chemistry and Biochemistry, Laboratory of Qualitative Analytical Chemistry, Laboratory Technology chemical and others.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="73">
        <source>A área de desenho esteve presente nos planos curriculares dos alunos desde a criação da Escola Industrial do Porto em 1852. O seu ensino compreendia a execução do desenho à vista ou mão livre, ou com auxílio de instrumentos de precisão para desenho rigoroso.</source>
        <target>Since the first days of the Industrial School of Oporto in 1852 that Drawing is a subject enclosed in the curriculum. It included the implementation of the design view, sketch, and geometric drawing. </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="74">
        <source>Ao longo da segunda metade do séc. XIX e séc. XX o ensino do desenho foi-se ajustando às necessidades do ensino industrial.</source>
        <target>Throughout the second half of the nineteenth and twentieth century the teaching of Drawing was adjusted to the needs of industrial education.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="75">
        <source>No museu podem ser observados diversos materiais tais como plantas topográﬁcas, palacetes, quadrantes, réguas de cálculo, entre outros.</source>
        <target>At the museum can be seen different items such as topographical plans, palaces, quadrants, slide rules, among others.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="76">
        <source>A aula de desenho surgiu com o intuito de permitir aos alunos adquirirem capacidade na linguagem gráfica, ou seja, o seu principal objetivo era tornar os alunos capazes de compreender o uso das formas e cores nas suas aplicações.</source>
        <target>The Drawing lesson has emerged in order to give the students the ability to obtain in graphic language, and to make the students capable of understanding the use of shapes and colors in their applications.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="77">
        <source>O ensino era efetuado de duas formas: com o auxílio de instrumentos de precisão, denominado de desenho rigoroso, e por intermédio de mão livre denominado de desenho à vista.</source>
        <target>The teaching was done in two different ways: with the aid of precision instruments, the rigorous drawing and through sketch called the drawing in sight. </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="78">
        <source>No início do século XX, Portugal juntamente com os países mais desenvolvidos, implementou um conjunto de regras a nível da quantidade e qualidade dos instrumentos de desenho, começando assim esta metodologia a merecer destaque em manuais de instrução.</source>
        <target>In the early twentieth century, Portugal along with more developed countries, implemented a set of rules in terms of quantity and quality of drawing instruments, beginning this methodology to be highlighted in teaching books.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="79">
        <source>De 1852 a 1864 existia uma cadeira obrigatória de desenho em todos os cursos e em todos os graus, dando-se assim uma enorme relevância ao desenho. Ao longo dos anos e até à data de hoje várias mudanças foram ocorrendo em torno do programa letivo dos cursos, onde gradualmente as disciplinas de desenho foram perdendo uma grande importância.</source>
        <target>From 1852 to 1864 there was a compulsory Drawing subject in all courses and all degrees, giving then a huge relevance to drawing. Over the years and up to this time several changes occurred and the drawing, as a subject, has been losing its importance.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="80">
        <source>Hoje em dia, apenas as licenciaturas de Engenharia Geotécnica, Geoambiente e Mecânica apresentam no seu plano de estudos uma cadeira de desenho técnico.</source>
        <target>Nowadays, only the degrees of Geotechnical Engineering, Geo-Environmental and Mechanics have in its plan of studies the subject of Technical Drawing.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="81">
        <source>A mecânica, associada ao estudo das máquinas, surge em 1852 com a cadeira de Desenho de Modelos de Máquinas presente nos cursos de Oficial Mecânico e de Diretor Mecânico.</source>
        <target>The subject of mechanics associated with the study of machines, appeared in 1852 with the subject Machine Models Design present in the Mechanical Official and Mechanical Chief degrees.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="82">
        <source>Atualmente a coleção é composta por modelos de distribuição de vapor, modelos de máquinas a vapor, diversas peças de máquinas e modelos de engrenagens. Possui ainda uma coleção de modelos do Sistema Reuleaux pertencentes ao Museu Tecnológico criado pelo decreto de 1864.</source>
        <target>Nowadays the collection consists of models of steam distribution, models of steam engines,  and various types of machine parts and gears. It also has a collection of Reuleaux models of the system belonging to the Technological Museum created by the decree of 1864.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="83">
        <source>A mecânica surgiu em 1852 na Escola com a cadeira de Desenhos de Modelos de Máquinas e com os cursos de Oficial Mecânico e de Diretor Mecânico.</source>
        <target>The area of mechanics emerged in 1852 with the subject of Machine Models Design with the Mechanical Official and Mechanical Chief degrees.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="84">
        <source>Em 1853 surge a primeira informação sobre a existência de um Gabinete de Máquinas, mas apenas mais tarde, em 1880 é que voltam a existir registos de atividade do mesmo.</source>
        <target>In 1853 the first information about the existence of a Machine Office comes out, but only in 1880 there are records that register the activity of the same.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="85">
        <source>Após a reforma de 1886 é criado o Laboratório Mecânico, que servia de suporte à cadeira de Mecânica e à Investigação. A partir de 1931 o Curso de Máquinas juntou-se ao de Eletrotecnia.</source>
        <target>After the reform of 1886 the Mechanical Laboratory is created, which served as support to the subject of Mechanical Engineering and Research. Since 1931 the degree of Machinery  joined the Electrotechnology.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="86">
        <source>Atualmente, e depois de várias reformas no ensino, podemos constatar que o plano de estudos do curso de Engenharia Mecânica continua a ter cadeiras como Eletricidade, Máquinas Elétricas e Órgãos de Máquinas, áreas estas que têm vindo a ser abordadas pelos alunos desde o início do século XIX.</source>
        <target>At present, and after several education reforms, it seems that the curriculum of the Mechanical Engineering persists to have subjects such as Electricity, Electrical Machines and Organs Machinery, which have been supported by students from the beginning of  the nineteenth century.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="87">
        <source>A primeira referência à área de civil aparece em 1864, na primeira reforma do ensino industrial, quando é criado o curso de Condutores de Obras Públicas e 6ª cadeira – Construções Civis e Tecnologia Geral.</source>
        <target>The first reference to the subject of Civil appears in 1864, in the first reform of industrial education, by that time the degree of Conductors of Public Works and the 6th subject – Civil Constructions and General Technology were created.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="88">
        <source>A coleção existente no museu é composta por modelos de pontes e viadutos, modelos de rodas hidráulicas, turbinas, comportas.</source>
        <target>The present museum collection consists of composed of models of bridges and viaducts, models of water wheels, turbines and floodgates. </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="89">
        <source>Apenas em 1864, após a primeira reforma do ensino industrial, aparece a primeira referência à área de Civil. Posteriormente não existe qualquer referência a um gabinete e/ou laboratório específico nesta área.</source>
        <target>Only in 1864, after the first industrial education reform, appears the first reference to the Civil subject. Subsequently there is no reference to an office and/or laboratory specific to this subject.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="90">
        <source>Em 1898 o Gabinete de Construções estava situado no extinto Convento das Carmelitas, juntamente com a aula de pintura, as oficinas de serralharia e carpintaria e a aula de mecânica.</source>
        <target>In 1898 the Office of Buildings was located in the extinct Convento das Carmelitas, along with the painting class, the workshops of locksmith and carpentry and the mechanics class.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="91">
        <source>No início do século XX foi criado o curso de Construções Civis e Obras Públicas, que apenas foi alterado em 1931 quando passou a incorporar as Minas, passando assim a denominar-se de Obras Públicas e Minas.</source>
        <target>In the early twentieth century the degree of Civil Construction and Public Works was created, and in 1931 changed its name to Public Works and Mines.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="92">
        <source>No ano de 1950, para dar apoio ao curso de Construção Civil e Minas, foram criados dois gabinetes, o de Resistência de Materiais e Estabilidade e o de Materiais de Construção e Cimento Armado.</source>
        <target>In the year 1950, to support the degree of Civil Construction and Mining, two offices were created: the Resistance and Stability of Materials and Construction Materials and Reinforced Cement.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="93">
        <source>Gabinete de Mineralogia e Arte de Minas</source>
        <target>Office of Mineralogy and Art of Mines</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="94">
        <source>A arte de minas no século XIX era vista como um fator importante para o progresso da Sociedade. Só em 1864, esta área integrou o plano de estudos. Também neste ano surgem registos sobre o Gabinete de Mineralogia, embora não constem nos respetivos decretos. Em 1869 esta área ganha relevância no Porto ao ser decretado o Curso de Condutores de Minas e de Mestres Mineiros, sendo unicamente lecionado nesta cidade. O Gabinete de Mineralogia e Arte de Minas foi criado em 1886, mas no ano seguinte passou a denominar-se apenas de Gabinete de Arte e de Minas.</source>
        <target>In the nineteenth century the art of Mines was seen as an important factor for the progress of Society, but it only became a part of the curriculum in 1864. Also in this year arise records on the Office of Mineralogy, although not listed in the respective decrees. In 1869, in Oporto began the course of Conductors of Mines and Miners Masters. It is important to refer that this course was only taught in Oporto. The Office of Mineralogy and Art of Mines was created in 1886, and was renamed  Office of Art and Mines a year after.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="95">
        <source>Já em 1888 por intermédio do Professor Miranda Júnior é realizada a instalação do Gabinete de Arte de Minas e Metalurgia. A importância destes Laboratórios foi enorme, pois os alunos tinham possibilidade de encontrar modelos das grandes inovações tecnológicas da época. Ao longo dos restantes anos foram surgindo inúmeras reformas a nível destas áreas, sendo lecionadas em diversos cursos, como por exemplo o curso de Construção Civil e Minas, nos anos cinquenta. Desde 1975 existe no Instituto o Departamento de Engenharia Geotécnica (DEG), com a Licenciatura em Geotécnica e Geoambiente, onde as áreas de Mineralogia e Minas ainda são abordadas.</source>
        <target>In 1888 the Professor Miranda Junior made the installation of the Office of Art of Mines and Metallurgy. The importance of these laboratories was enormous, because the students had the  possibility to find models of the major technological innovations of the time.  Over the following years there were many reforms on the subjects which were taught in different courses, namely the Civil Construction and Mines degree. Since 1975 there is in the Institute a Department of Geotechnical Engineering (DGE), with the degree in Geotechnical and Geo-Environmental, where the Mineralogy and Mine subjects are still addressed. </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="96">
        <source>A coleção é composta por modelos de revestimentos de galerias, poços verticais, ventiladores de minas, modelos de bombas centrífugas, minérios, modelos de lavra de minas, modelos de fornos e de aparelhos de perfuração, modelos de recuperação de ar quente, modelos de aparelhos metalúrgicos e outros aparelhos e mecanismos empregues nas minas.</source>
        <target>The collection consist of models of coatings of galleries, vertical wells, mine fans, centrifugal pumps models, ores, models of pit mining, models of furnaces and drilling equipment, hot air recovery models, models of metallurgical equipment and other apparatus and mechanisms employed in mines. </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="97">
        <source>Gabinete de Hidráulica</source>
        <target>Office of Hydraulics</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="98">
        <source>A Hidráulica assumiu um papel importante em grande parte dos cursos lecionados neste Instituto.</source>
        <target>The Hydraulic took an important role in most degrees taught in this Institute. </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="99">
        <source>Inicialmente o estudo desta temática era dividida em duas grandes partes, em que a primeira era dedicada aos aspetos relacionados com o uso no contexto diário da Hidráulica. A segunda era dedicada à aplicabilidade e estudo da Hidráulica no contexto mais específico dos rios, canais e portos do mar.</source>
        <target>Initially the study of this theme was divided into two major parts, the aspects related to the use of Hydraulics in its daily context and applicability and study of Hydraulics in the specific context of the rivers, canals and sea harbors. </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="100">
        <source>Contudo, após a reforma do ensino industrial e comercial de 1919 o estudo da Hidráulica passou a ser dividido em três partes. A primeira parte refere o estudo da Hidráulica em geral, urbana e agrícola, sendo uma disciplina mais teórica e de cálculo; a segunda parte era referente à hidráulica mecânica e aplicações do ar comprimido e da água em pressão, esta tinha uma componente orientada para a utilidade da hidráulica no aproveitamento da água; A terceira parte era responsável pelo estudo de rios e portos do mar, onde o seu principal objetivo, como o nome indica, tratava do estudo dos rios nas suas diferentes tipologias, partes que o constituem e da utilização e proteção dos mesmos.</source>
        <target>However, after the reform of industrial and commercial education in 1919, the study of Hydraulic was divided into three parts. The first part refers to the study of Hydraulic in general, urban and agricultural, a more theoretical and calculation discipline; the second part refers to hydraulic mechanics and applications of  air compressed and water pressure, with a component directed to the usefulness of hydraulics in the use of water; the third part was responsible for the study of rivers and sea harbors, where its main objective, as the name indicates, was the study of rivers in its different typologies, its different parts and its use and protection.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="101">
        <source>A partir de 1919 a cadeira dedicada ao ensino da Hidráulica fazia parte do Curso Especializado de Construções Civis e Obras Públicas, do Curso Especializado de Minas, do Curso Especializado de Máquinas e do Curso Especializado de Eletrotecnia.</source>
        <target>Since 1919 the subject dedicated to the teaching of Hydraulic was included on the specialized degrees of: Civil Construction and Public Works, Mines, Machines and Electrotechnology.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="102">
        <source>Em 1927 o plano curricular sofre alterações, mantendo-se de igual forma as três partes da cadeira, embora sofrendo uma substancial alteração.</source>
        <target>In 1927 the syllabus had changes, keeping the same way in the three parts of the discipline, although suffering a substantial change.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="103">
        <source>Desde 1919 e até à data de hoje a cadeira manteve-se sempre dívida em três partes, com campos de estudo bastante específicos. Contudo, graças à evolução humana, científica e tecnológica, foram existindo bastantes reformas ao longo dos anos, o que fez com que estas três partes fossem sofrendo ligeiras adaptações, de forma a adequarem-se à atualidade.</source>
        <target>Since 1919 and until today the subject has always remained divided into three parts, with very specific fields of study. However, due to human evolution, science and technology, there were plenty of reforms over the years, which made that these three parts have been suffering some adjustments in order to adapt themselves to the present day. </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="104">
        <source>Horário de Funcionamento</source>
        <target>Schedule</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="105">
        <source>Segunda a Sexta-feira</source>
        <target>Monday to Friday</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="106">
        <source>Entrada Gratuita</source>
        <target>Free Admission</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="107">
        <source>Marcação de Grupos</source>
        <target>To Schedule Group Visits</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="108">
        <source>Introdução</source>
        <target>Introduction</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="109">
        <source>O Museu no teu telemóvel</source>
        <target>The Museum in your phone</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="110">
        <source>Peça em destaque</source>
        <target>Featured piece</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="111">
        <source>Ver mapa maior</source>
        <target>Increasing map</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="112">
        <source>Objectos</source>
        <target>Objects</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="113">
        <source>Estampagens</source>
        <target>Stampings</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="114">
        <source>Catálogo: estampagens</source>
        <target>Catalog: stampings</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="115">
        <source>Catálogo: objectos</source>
        <target>Catalog: objects</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="116">
        <source>Telefone:</source>
        <target>Phone:</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="117">
        <source>Fax:</source>
        <target>Fax:</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="118">
        <source>E-mail:</source>
        <target>E-mail:</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="119">
        <source>Voto inserido com sucesso.</source>
        <target>Successfully rated.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="120">
        <source>Voto actualizado com sucesso.</source>
        <target>Successfully updated.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="121">
        <source>Editar votação de objecto</source>
        <target>Edit rating</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="122">
        <source>Votar</source>
        <target>Rating</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="123">
        <source>Votação</source>
        <target>Rating</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="124">
        <source>Votar objecto</source>
        <target>Rating object</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="125">
        <source>Eventos</source>
        <target>Events</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="126">
        <source>Local: </source>
        <target>Local: </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="127">
        <source>De </source>
        <target>By </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="128">
        <source> a </source>
        <target> to </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="129">
        <source>Comentário inserido com sucesso.</source>
        <target>Successfully commented.</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="130">
        <source>Editar comentário</source>
        <target>Edit comment</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="131">
        <source>Inserir</source>
        <target>Insert</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="132">
        <source>Comentar objecto</source>
        <target>Comment object</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="133">
        <source>Ver Objecto</source>
        <target>Show Object</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="134">
        <source>Comentar</source>
        <target>Comment</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="135">
        <source>Votação (</source>
        <target>Rating (</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="136">
        <source> Total de votos: </source>
        <target> Total votes: </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="137">
        <source>Descrição</source>
        <target>Overview</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="138">
        <source>Finalidade</source>
        <target>Finality</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="139">
        <source>Localização</source>
        <target>Location</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="140">
        <source>Comentários</source>
        <target>Comments</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="141">
        <source>Efectuado por: </source>
        <target>By: </target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="142">
        <source>Telefone/Fax</source>
        <target>Phone/Fax</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="143">
        <source>Email</source>
        <target>Email</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="144">
        <source>O Museu nas redes sociais</source>
        <target>The Museum in the social network</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="145">
        <source>Ver Estampagem</source>
        <target>Show Stamping</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="146">
        <source>Designação</source>
        <target>Designation</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="147">
        <source>Tipologia</source>
        <target>Typology</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="148">
        <source>Autor</source>
        <target>Author</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="149">
        <source>Materiais</source>
        <target>Materials</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="150">
        <source>Técnicas</source>
        <target>Tecniques</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="151">
        <source>Cores</source>
        <target>Colors</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="152">
        <source>Editar votação de Estampagem</source>
        <target>Edit stamping rating</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="153">
        <source>Votar Estampagem</source>
        <target>Rating Stamping</target>
      </trans-unit>
      <trans-unit id="154">
        <source>Comentar Estampagem</source>
        <target>Comment Stamping</target>
      </trans-unit>
    </body>
  </file>
</xliff>
